I'm going to go off script
سأخرج عن النص
and make Chris quite nervous here
و أجعل كريس متوترا قليلاً
by making this audience participation.
بالسماح للجمهور بالمشاركة
All right. Are you with me? Yeah. Yeah. All right.
حستًا؟ هل أنتم معي؟ نعم .. نعم .. حسنًا
So what I'd like to do is have you raise your hand
كل ما أريدكم أن تفعلوه هو أن ترفعوا أيديكم
if you've ever heard a heterosexual couple having sex.
إذا سمعتم من قبل عن شخصين يمارسان الجنس
Could be the neighbors, hotel room,
من المحتمل أن يكونا جيران .. في غرفة فندق
your parents. Sorry.
أو والديكم. آسف.
Okay. Pretty much everybody.
إذا .. الجميع تقريبًا
Now raise your hand if the man was making
الآن ارفعوا ايديكم إذا كان الرجل هو من يصنع
more noise than the woman.
ضوضاء أكثر من المرأة
I see one guy there.
أنا آرى شخص وحيد
It doesn't count if it was you, sir.
لا يحسب إذا كنت أنت, سيدي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So his hand's down. And one woman. Okay.
لقد أنزل يده .. و إمرآة واحدة .. حسنًا
Sitting next to a loud guy.
تجلس بجوار رجل مزعج
Now what does this tell us?
إذا ما الذي نستنتجه من هذا؟
It tells us that human beings
هذا يخبرنا ان البشر
make noise when they have sex,
يصنعون أصواتًا حينما يمارسون الجنس
and it's generally the woman who makes more noise.
و بشكل عام النساء تصنعن أصواتًا أكتر
This is known as female copulatory vocalization
هذا يعرف بـ "التعبير الصوتي الانثوي المصاحب للجنس"
to the clipboard crowd.
لمعرفة الجمهور
I wasn't even going to mention this,
أنا لم أرد ذكر ذلك
but somebody told me that Meg Ryan might be here,
لكن شخصًا ما أخبرني أن "ميج رايان" من الممكن أن تكون هنا
and she is the world's most famous
و هي الأكثر شهرة عالميًا
female copulatory vocalizer.
كأنثى مصدر أصوات مصاحبة للجنس
So I thought, got to talk about that.
لذا فقد ظننت أنه يجب على التحدث عن ذلك
We'll get back to that a little bit later.
و لكننا سنعود لذلك لاحقًا
Let me start by saying human beings
علىّ أن أبدأ بذكر أن البشر
are not descended from apes,
لم يتطوروا عن القردة
despite what you may have heard. We are apes.
بالرغم مما قد سمعته من قبل. نحن قردة
We are more closely related to the chimp and the bonobo
نحن أكثر قرابة للشمبانزي و قرد البونوبو
than the African elephant is to the Indian elephant,
من القرابة بين الفيل الأفريقي و الفيل الهندي
as Jared Diamond pointed out in one of his early books.
كما أشار "جاريد داياموند" في أحد أول كتبه
We're more closely related to chimps and bonobos
بأننا أكثر قرابة للشمبانزي و البونوبو
than chimps and bonobos are related
من قرابتهما لبعضهما البعض
to any other primate --
لأي حيوان رئيسي آخر --
gorillas, orangutans, what have you.
الغوريلا, القردة, و ما إلى ذلك.
So we're extremely closely related to them,
إذا فنحن قريبين جدًا لهم,
and as you'll see in terms of our behavior,
وكما سنرى من ناحية سلوكنا,
we've got some relationship as well.
لنا علاقة بهم أيضًا.
So what I'm asking today, the question
إذا ما أطلبه اليوم .. السؤال
I want to explore with you today is,
الذي أريد ان أكتشفه معكم اليوم هو
what kind of ape are we in terms of our sexuality?
من أي نوع من القردة نحن من ناحية سلوكنا الجنسي؟
Now, since Darwin's day there's been
إذا من وقت دارون هناك
what Cacilda and I have called
ما سميناه أنا و كاسيلدا
the standard narrative of human sexual evolution,
معيار التطور الجنسي للإنسان,
and you're all familiar with it,
و أظن أنكم جميعًا تعرفونه,
even if you haven't read this stuff.
حتى إذا لم تقرؤا عنه.
The idea is that, as part of human nature,
الفكرة هي ان جزء من الطبيعة البشرية,
from the beginning of our species' time,
من بداية نشأة نوعنا الحالي,
men have sort of leased women's reproductive potential
الرجال قد احتكروا قدرات المرأة الإنجابية
by providing them with certain goods and services.
في مقابل تزويدهن بالمنتجات والخدمات.
Generally we're talking about meat, shelter, status,
بشكل عام نحن نتحدث عن اللحم, المسكن. و المكانة,
protection, things like that.
الحماية, وأشياء أخرى مشابهة.
And in exchange, women have offered fidelity,
وفي المقابل, قدمت النساء الإخلاص
or at least a promise of fidelity.
أو على الأقل وعد بالإخلاص.
Now this sets men and women up in an oppositional relationship.
و هذا يجعل الرجل و المراة في علاقة تعارضية.
The war between the sexes is built right into our DNA, according to this vision. Right?
الحرب بين الجنسين مزروعة في حمضنا النووي بناءً على هذه الرؤية. أليس كذلك؟
What Cacilda and I have argued is that no,
ما نجادل به أنا وكاسيلدا أن ذلك غير صحيح
this economic relationship,
هذه العلاقة الاقتصادية,
this oppositional relationship,
والعلاقة التعارضية,
is actually an artifact of agriculture,
هي في الواقع نتيجة لعملية الزراعة,
which only arose about 10,000 years ago at the earliest.
التي نشأت من حوالي عشرة آلاف سنة.
Anatomically modern human beings
الإنسان الحديث "الحالي"
have been around for about 200,000 years,
موجود منذ حوالي مئتا ألف سنة,
so we're talking about five percent, at most,
إذا فنحن نتكلم عن خمسة بالمائة تقريبًا
of our time as a modern, distinct species.
من عمرنا كنوع متطور منفصل
So before agriculture,
إذا قبيل اكتشاف الزراعة
before the agricultural revolution,
قبل الثورة الزراعية
it's important to understand that human beings
من المهم معرفة ان الانسان
lived in hunter-gatherer groups that are
تواجد في مجموعات صيد-جمع
characterized wherever they're found in the world
تتميز أيًا كان موقعها في العالم
by what anthropologists called fierce egalitarianism.
بما سماه علماء الانثروبولوجيا "علم الانسان" بـ المساواة الشرسة
They not only share things,
هم لا يتشاركون الأشياء و فقط
they demand that things be shared:
بل يطالبون بمشاركة هذه الأشياء
meat, shelter, protection, all these things
اللحم و الملجأ و الحماية .. كل تلك الأشياء
that were supposedly being traded to women
التي كانت من المفترض انها تمنح للإناث
for their sexual fidelity, it turns out,
مقابل الولاء الجنسي, فتصبح
are shared widely among these societies.
متداولة بشكل أوسع عبر تلك المجتمعات
Now I'm not saying that our ancestors
الآن انا لا أقصد ان أجدادنا
were noble savages, and I'm not saying
كانوا همجيين ذوي نُبل, ولا أقول
modern day hunter-gatherers are noble savages either.
أن خلفاؤهم الحاليين نبلاء همجيين أيضًا
What I'm saying is that this is simply
ما أقوله هو أن هذه بكل بساطة
the best way to mitigate risk
هي أفضل طريقة لتخفيف المخاطر
in a foraging context.
في عملية البحث عن المؤن.
And there's really no argument about this among anthropologists.
ولا يوجد خلاف بخصوص هذا بين علماء الانثروبولوجيا.
All Cacilda and I have done is extend this sharing behavior to sexuality.
ما فعلناه أنا و كاسيلدا اننا طبقنا ذلك السلوك على الحياة الجنسية.
So we've argued that human sexuality
إذا فقد اقترحنا أن السلوك الجنسي البشري
has essentially evolved, until agriculture,
تطور بشكل أساسي, حتى اكتشاف عملية الزراعة,
as a way of establishing and maintaining
على شكل طريقة لتأسيس و الإبقاء على
the complex, flexible social systems, networks,
الأنظمة الاجتماعية المعقدة والمرنة, الشبكات
that our ancestors were very good at,
التي كان أجدادنا متميزين فيها,
and that's why our species has survived so well.
و لهذا السبب قد نجح نوعنا في البقاء حتى الآن,
Now, this makes some people uncomfortable,
الآن, هذا يجعل البعض قلقين,
and so I always need to take a moment in these talks
و لهذا فأنا دائمًا أحتاج أن اتوقف للحظة في هذه الخطابات
to say, listen,
لأقول .. أنصتوا
I'm saying our ancestors were promiscuous,
انا أقول ان أجدادنا كانوا عديدي الشركاء الجنسيين
but I'm not saying they were having sex with strangers.
لكن لا أقول انهم كانوا يمارسون الجنس مع الغرباء
There were no strangers. Right?
لم يكن هناك غرباء. أليس كذلك؟
In a hunter-gatherer band, there are no strangers.
في القبيلة لا يوجد غرباء
You've known these people your entire life.
لقد عرفت هؤلاء الناس طوال حياتك
So I'm saying, yes, there were overlapping sexual relationships,
إذا أنا أقول أنه .. نعم .. كانت هناك علاقات جنسية معقدة و متداخلة
that our ancestors probably had several different sexual relationships
ان أجدادنا غالبًا قد مارسوا الجنس مع العديد من الأشخاص
going on at any given moment in their adult lives.
بشكل مستمر خلال حياتهم كبالغين
But I'm not saying they were having sex with strangers.
لكني لا أقول انهم كانوا يمارسون الجنس مع غرباء
I'm not saying that they didn't love the people they were having sex with.
لا أقول أنهم كانوا لا يحبون الأشخاص الذين يمارسون معهم الجنس
And I'm not saying there was no pair-bonding going on.
أيضًا لم أنفي ان توجد علاقات عاطفية مستمرة
I'm just saying it wasn't sexually exclusive.
انا أقول انها لم تكُن علاقات احتكارية
And those of us who have chosen to be monogamous --
و اننا من اخترنا ان تكون علاقاتنا احادية احتكارية
my parents, for example, have been married
والدي, على سبيل المثال, تزوجا
for 52 years monogamously,
لـ 52 سنة بلا أي شركاء آخرين
and if it wasn't monogamously, Mom and Dad,
و إذا لم تكن علاقتها بهذا الشكل. والدي و والدتي,
I don't want to hear about it—
"انا لا أريد ان أسمع ذلك"
I'm not criticizing this and I'm not saying
انا لا انتقد ذلك ولا أقول ان
there's anything wrong with this.
هناك شيء خاطئ في ذلك
What I'm saying is that to argue
ما أقوله فقط هو ان اناقش
that our ancestors were sexual omnivores
ان أجدادنا كانوا جنسيين للغاية
is no more a criticism of monogamy
هذا ليس نقد لأحادية الشريك الجنسي
than to argue that our ancestors were dietary omnivores
أكثر من ادعاء أن أجدادنا كانوا آكلين للحم
is a criticism of vegetarianism.
هو نقد للنباتية
You can choose to be a vegetarian,
يمكنك اختيار ان تكون نباتيًا
but don't think that just because you've made that decision,
و لكن لا تظن ان باختيارك هذا
bacon suddenly stops smelling good.
يكون اللحم قد توقف فجأة عن كونه طيب الرائحة
Okay? So this is my point.
حسنا؟ هذا هو ما أقصده
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That one took a minute to sink in, huh?
لقد أخذ ذلك وقتًا للاستيعاب, أليس كذلك؟
Now, in addition to being a great genius,
الآن بالإضافة لكونه عبقريًا
a wonderful man, a wonderful husband,
رجل رائع .. زوج رائع
a wonderful father, Charles Darwin
أب رائع .. تشارلز دارون
was also a world-class Victorian prude.
كان رجل ذو شأن على مستوى عالمي
All right? He was perplexed
حسنا؟ لقد كان مرتبك
by the sexual swellings of certain primates,
بشأن التورم الجنسي عند بعض الرئيسيات
including chimps and bonobos,
التي تشمل الشمبانزي و البونوبو
because these sexual swellings tend to provoke
لان هذه التورمات تثير
many males to mate with the females.
الكثير من الذكور لممارسة الجنس مع الإناث
So he couldn't understand why on Earth would the female have developed this thing
لذلك فهو لم يستطع ان يفهم لماذا طورت الاناث هذا الشيء
if all they were supposed to be doing is forming their pair bond, right?
إذا كان المطلوب منهم فقط ان يكونوا علاقات زوجية, أليس كذلك؟
Chimps and bonobos, Darwin didn't really know this,
الشمبانزي و البونوبو. داروين لم يكن يعرف ذلك
but chimps and bonobos mate
و لكن الشمبانزي و البونوبو يمارسون الجنس
one to four times per hour
من مرة لأربع مرات كل ساعة
with up to a dozen males per day
مع أكثر من درزن من الذكور كل يوم
when they have their sexual swellings.
عندما يكون لديهم تورمات جنسية
Interestingly, chimps have sexual swellings
من المثير للاهتمام, أن الشمبانزي لديهم تورمات جنسية
through 40 percent, roughly,
بنسبة 40% تقريبا,
of their menstrual cycle,
من الدورة الشهرية الخاصة بهم,
bonobos 90 percent,
البونوبو 90%,
and humans are among the only species on the planet
والبشر من بين الأنواع الوحيدة في هذا الكوكب
where the female is available for sex
حيث الأنثى متاحة للجنس
throughout the menstrual cycle,
طوال دورة الطمث,
whether she's menstruating, whether she's post-menopausal,
سواء أنها حائض, سواء أنها بعد انقطاع الطمث,
whether she's already pregnant.
أو حتى لو كانت حاملا.
This is vanishingly rare among mammals.
وهذا أمر نادر الحدوث بين الثدييات
So it's a very interesting aspect of human sexuality.
لذلك هو جانب مثير جدا للاهتمام من النشاط الجنسي البشري.
Now, Darwin ignored the reflections
الآن, داروين تجاهل الانعكاسات المتعلقة
of the sexual swelling in his own day,
بالتورمات الجنسية خلال يومه الخاص,
as scientists tend to do sometimes.
كما يميل العلماء أن يفعلوا في بعض الأحيان.
So what we're talking about is sperm competition.
لذا الأمر الذي نتحدث عنه هو منافسة حيوانات منوية.
Now the average human ejaculate has about 300 million sperm cells,
الآن متوسط القذف لدى البشر حوالي 300 مليون خلية حيوان منوي,
so it's already a competitive environment.
لذلك فهي بيئة تنافسية أساسا
The question is whether these sperm are competing against other men's sperm
السؤال هو ما إذا كانت هذه الحيوانات المنوية تتنافس ضد حيوانات منوية لرجال آخرين
or just their own.
أو فقط حيوانات منوية لذات الشخص فقط
There's a lot to talk about in this chart.
هنالك الكثير من الكلام للحديث عنه في هذا الرسم البياني
The one thing I'll call your attention to right away
الشيء الوحيد الذي أود لفت انتباهكم إليه فورا
is the little musical note above the female chimp and bonobo and human.
هو النوتة الموسيقية الصغيرة فوق أنثى الشمبانزي والبونوبو والإنسان
That indicates female copulatory vocalization.
والتي تشير إلى أن الإناث متصلات النطق
Just look at the numbers.
فقط انظروا ‘إلى الأرقام
The average human has sex
معدل ممارسة الإنسان للجنس
about 1,000 times per birth.
حوالي 1000 مرة مقابل كل حالة ولادة
If that number seems high for some of you,
إن كان هذا الرقم يبدو عاليا بالنسبة لبعضكم
I assure you it seems low for others in the room.
أنا أوكد لكم بأنه يبدو منخفضا للآخرين في الغرفة.
We share that ratio with chimps and bonobos.
ونحن نشاطر هذه النسبة (ممارسة الجنس) مع الشمبانزي والبونوبو.
We don't share it with the other three apes,
ولكننا لا نشاطرها مع الأنواع الثلاثة الأخرى للقرود,
the gorilla, the orangutan and the gibbon,
الغوريلا, إنسان الغاب والجيبون,
who are more typical of mammals,
والذين يعدون أكثر نموذجية للثدييات,
having sex only about a dozen times per birth.
معدل ممارستهم للجنس هو 12 مرة لكل حالة ولادة,
Humans and bonobos are the only animals that have sex face-to-face
بنو البشر والبونوبو هما الحيوانات الوحيدة التي تمارس الجنس وجها لوجه
when both of them are alive.
وعندما يكون كل منهما على قيد الحياة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you'll see that the human, chimp and bonobo
وسوف ترون أن البشر, الشمبانزي والبونوبو
all have external testicles, which in our book
جميعهم يملكون خصيتين خارجيتين, حيث أنها في كتابنا
we equate to a special fridge you have in the garage
نعادلها بثلاجة خاصة تملكونها في المرآب
just for beer.
فقط للجعة
If you're the kind of guy who has a beer fridge
إذا كنت من النوع الذي يملك ثلاجة جعة
in the garage, you expect a party to happen
في المرآب, أنت تتوقع حدوث حفلة
at any moment, and you need to be ready.
في أي لحظة, وعليك أن تكون جاهزا لذلك.
That's what the external testicles are.
وهذا ما نعنيه بالخصيتين الخارجيتين.
They keep the sperm cells cool
إنها تبقي خلايا الحيوانات المنوية هادئة
so you can have frequent ejaculations.
حتى تتمكن من القذف المتكرر
I'm sorry. It's true.
أنا آسف. ذلك صحيح.
The human, some of you will be happy to hear,
البشر, بعضكم سيكون سعيدا عندما يسمع
has the largest, thickest penis of any primate.
البشر يملكون القضيب الأكثر سمكا من بين الحيوانات
Now, this evidence goes way beyond anatomy.
الآن, هذا الدليل يذهب إلى طريق ما بعد علم التشريح
It goes into anthropology as well.
إنه يذهب إلى علم الإنسان كذلك.
Historical records are full of accounts of people
السجلات التاريخية مليئة بحساب الناس
around the world who have sexual practices
حول العالم والذين يملكون الممارسات الجنسية
that should be impossible
ذلك لابد أن يكون مستحيلا
given what we have assumed about human sexual evolution.
بالنظر إلى ما افترضنا حول التطور الجنسي البشري
These women are the Mosuo from southwestern China.
أولئك النساء الذين يدعون بالموسو من جنوب غرب الصين
In their society, everyone, men and women,
في مجتمعهم, كل واحد, رجال ونساء,
are completely sexually autonomous.
مستقلين تماما عن طريق الاتصال الجنسي
There's no shame associated with sexual behavior.
ليس هنالك عار مرتبط بالسلوك الجنسي
Women have hundreds of partners.
النساء يملكون المئات من الشركاء
It doesn't matter. Nobody cares. Nobody gossips. It's not an issue.
ذلك لا يهم. لا أحد يهتم. لا أحد يثرثر. إنها ليست قضية.
When the woman becomes pregnant,
حينما تصبح المرأة حاملا,
the child is cared for by her, her sisters, and her brothers.
الطفل يتلقى رعايته بواسطتها, وأخواتها وأخوانها.
The biological father is a nonissue.
الأب البيولوجي ليس قضية
On the other side of the planet, in the Amazon,
على الجانب الآخر من الكوكب, في الأمازون
we've got many tribes which practice
لدينا العديد من القبائل التي تمارس
what anthropologists call partible paternity.
ما يسميه علماء الأنثروبولوجيا بـ "الأبوة القابلة للتقسيم"
These people actually believe --
هؤلاء الناس في الحقيقة يؤمنون --
and they have no contact among them,
وليس لديهم اتصال فيما بينهم
no common language or anything,
بلا لغة مشتركة ولا أي شيء,
so it's not an idea that spread,
لذا هي ليست فكرة انتشرت,
it's an idea that's arisen around the world --
هي فكرة نهضت حول العالم --
they believe that a fetus is literally made
هم يؤمنون بأن الجنين يتكون حرفيا
of accumulated semen.
من السوائل المنوية المتراكمة
So a woman who wants to have a child
لذلك المرأة التي تريد أن تملك طفلا
who's smart and funny and strong
ذكيا ومضحكا وقويا
makes sure she has lots of sex with the smart guy,
ينبغي عليها أن تتاكد أنها مارست الكثير من الجنس مع شخص ذكي,
the funny guy and the strong guy,
وشخص مضحك وشخص قوي,
to get the essence of each of these men into the baby,
لتحصل على جوهر كل من هؤلاء الرجال داخل طفلها,
and then when the child is born,
وحينما يولد الطفل,
these different men will come forward
سيأتي هؤلاء الثلاثة رجال
and acknowledge their paternity of the child.
ويعترفون بأبوتهم على الطفل.
So paternity is actually sort of a team endeavor
لذا الأبوة في الواقع هي نوع من مسعى الفريق
in this society.
في هذا المجتمع
So there are all sorts of examples like this
لذا هنالك كل أنواع الأمثلة المشابهة لذلك
that we go through in the book.
نمر عليها خلال الكتاب
Now, why does this matter?
الآن, لماذا هذا يهم؟
Edward Wilson says we need to understand
إدوارد ويسلون قال إننا نحتاج أن نفهم
that human sexuality is first a bonding device
أن النشاط الجنسي البشري هو أولا جهاز ربط
and only secondarily procreation.
والإنجاب هو شكل ثانوي فقط.
I think that's true. This matters because
أعتقد أن ذلك صحيحا. هذا يهم لأن
our evolved sexuality is in direct conflict
حياتنا الجنسية في صراع مباشر
with many aspects of the modern world.
مع جوانب كثيرة من العالم الحديث.
The contradictions between what we're told
التناقضات بين ما قيل لنا
we should feel and what we actually do feel
بما يجب أن نشعر به وما نشعر به في الواقع
generates a huge amount of unnecessary suffering.
يولد كمية ضخمة من معاناة لا داعي لها.
My hope is that a more accurate,
أملي هو أكثر دقة,
updated understanding of human sexuality
تحديث فهم النشاط الجنسي البشري
will lead us to have greater tolerance for ourselves,
سيؤدي بنا إلى قدر أكبر من التسامح مع أنفسنا,
for each other,
لكل طرف,
greater respect for unconventional relationship configurations
مزيدا من الاحترام لتكوينات العلاقة الغير تقليدية
like same-sex marriage or polyamorous unions,
مثل الزواج من نفس الجنس أو نقابات البوليموروز
and that we'll finally put to rest the idea
وأخيرا في نهاية المطاف سنضع فكرة
that men have some innate, instinctive right
أن الرجال الذين لديهم بعض الفطرة, حق فطري
to monitor and control women's sexual behavior.
للرصد والتحكم بسلوك النساء الجنسي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
And we'll see that it's not only gay people
وسوف نرى ذلك أنه ليس فقط أصحاب الميل الجنسي من نفس النوع
that have to come out of the closet.
من يجب أن يخرجوا من الخزانة
We all have closets we have to come out of. Right?
جميعنا لدينا خزانات علينا أن نخرج منها. أليس كذلك؟
And when we do come out of those closets,
وحينما نخرج من تلك الخزانات
we'll recognize that our fight is not with each other,
سندرك بأن معركتنا ليست مع بعضنا البعض,
our fight is with an outdated, Victorian sense of human sexuality
معركتنا مع من عفى عليها الزمن, الشعور الفيكتوري من النشاط الجنسي البشري
that conflates desire with property rights,
الذي يخلط الرغبة مع شعور الملكية,
generates shame and confusion
يولد العار والارتباك
in place of understanding and empathy.
بدلا من التفاهم والتعاطف
It's time we moved beyond Mars and Venus,
حان الوقت لننتقل لما بعد المريخ والزهرة,
because the truth is
لأن الصدق هو
that men are from Africa
أن الرجال من أفريقيا
and women are from Africa.
والنساء من أفريقيا
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thank you. Christopher Ryan: Thank you.
كريس آندرسون: شكرا لك. كريستوفر ريان: شكرا لك.
CA: So a question.
كريس: سؤال.
It's so perplexing, trying to use arguments
إنه محير جدا, محاولة استخدام الحجج
about evolutionary history
حول التاريخ التطوري
to turn that into what we ought to do today.
لتحويل هذا إلى ما يجب علينا القيام به اليوم
Someone could give a talk and say,
ربما يقول أحدهم,
look at us, we've got these really sharp teeth
انظروا إلينا, لدينا أسنان حادة حقا
and muscles and a brain that's really good
وعضلات وعقل جيدون حقا
at throwing weapons,
في رمي الأسلحة,
and if you look at lots of societies around the world,
وحينما تنظر إلى الكثير من المجتمعات حول العالم,
you'll see very high rates of violence.
سترى نسبا عالية من العنف.
Nonviolence is a choice like vegetarianism,
عدم العنف هو خيار مثل النباتية,
but it's not who you are.
لكنه ليس من تكون.
How is that different
كيف يكون هذا مختلفا
from the talk you gave?
من الحديث الذي ألقيته؟
CR: Well first of all, the evidence
كريستوفر: حسنا, قبل كل شيء الدليل
for high levels of violence in prehistory
للمستويات العالية للعنف في عصر ما قبل التاريخ
is very debatable.
هو قابل للنقاش جدا.
But that's just an example.
لكن ذلك مجرد مثال.
Certainly, you know, lots of people say to me,
بكل تأكيد, كما تعلمون, الكثير من الناس يقولون لي
just because we lived a certain way in the past
فقط لأننا عشنا بطريقة معينة في الماضي
doesn't mean we should live that way now, and I agree with that.
لا يعني أننا ينبغي أن نعيش بنفس الطريقة الآن، وأنا اتفق مع ذلك.
Everyone has to respond to the modern world.
كل فرد عليه أن يستجيب إلى العالم الحديث.
But the body does have its inherent
ولكن الجسم يكون لديه
evolved trajectories.
مسارات تطوره المتأصلة
And so you could live on McDonald's and milkshakes,
وحتى يتمكن من العيش على ماكدونالدز وميلك شيك،
but your body will rebel against that. We have appetites.
ولكن جسمك سوف يتمرد ضد ذلك. لدينا شهية.
I think it was Schopenhauer who said,
أعتقد أنه كان شوبنهاور الذي قال:
a person can do what they want
الشخص يمكن أن يفعل ما يريده الآخرون
but not want what they want.
لكنه لا يمكن أن يريد ما يريده الآخرون
And so what I'm arguing against
وما أعترض عليه هو
is the shame that's associated with desires.
أن العار مرتبط بالرغبات.
It's the idea that if you love your husband or wife
إنها الفكرة أنه إذا كنت تحب زوجك أو زوجتك
but you still are attracted to other people,
ولكنك مازلت منجذبا إلى أشخاص آخرين،
there's something wrong with you,
هنالك شيء خاطئ معك،
there's something wrong with your marriage,
هنالك شيء خاطئ مع زواجك،
something wrong with your partner.
شيء خاطئ مع شريك حياتك.
I think a lot of families are fractured
أعتقد أن الكثير من الأسر مكسورة
by unrealistic expectations
بسبب التوقعات الغير واقعية
that are based upon this false vision of human sexuality.
التي تستند إلى تلك النظرة الخاطئة للنشاط الجنسي البشري.
That's what I'm trying to get at.
وهذا ما أحاول توضيحه.
CA: Thank you. Communicated powerfully. Thanks a lot.
كريس: شكرا لك. أبلغت بقوة. شكرًا جزيلاً.
CR: Thank you, Chris. (Applause)
كريستوفر: شكرا لك، كريس. (تصفيق)